<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature of justification opened in a sermon on Romans V. 1. By Mr. Gibbons, sometime preacher at Black-Fryers, London.</title>
            <author>Gibbon, John, 1629-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827988</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827988</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42685)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1925:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature of justification opened in a sermon on Romans V. 1. By Mr. Gibbons, sometime preacher at Black-Fryers, London.</title>
                  <author>Gibbon, John, 1629-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst, at the Bible and Three Crowns in Chepside, near Mercer's-Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Trinity College Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans V, 1 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NATURE OF JUSTIFICATION OPENED, IN A SERMON On ROMANS V. 1.</p>
            <p>BY Mr. <hi>GIBBONS,</hi> ſometime Preacher at <hi>Black-Fryers, LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst,</hi> at the <hi>Bible and Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercer</hi>'s-<hi>Chappel,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:32414:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32414:2"/>
            <head>The NATURE of <hi>Iuſtification opened.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROMANS V. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Therefore being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words preſent us, for the Argument of this Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Exerciſe, with the great Doctrine of Juſtification, firſt to be Opened, and then Improved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be Opened. And that we may not with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> and the Papiſts, <hi>In ipſo limine impingere,</hi> Stumble the very firſt Step we take, and ſo quite ever after loſe our way, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding Juſtification with Sanctification, I ſhall only premiſe, That as in Sanctification the change is Abſolute and Inherent, ſo in Juſtification the change is Relative and Juridical; the former is wrought in the Sinner's Perſon, he becomes a new Creature; but this latter is wrought in his State, he becomes Abſolved at the Bar of Divine Juſtice; for Juſtification is a Law-ſtate, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) it aboliſheth the convincing Power of Sin, or its Guilt. Our Buſineſs therefore, is to diſcover the Proceſs at God's Bar, in the juſtification of a Sinner, which will be beſt done by comparing it with that at Man's, which we are familiarly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanted with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To be Juſtified,</hi> therefore implies in general three things. 1. The Perſon is charg'd with Guilt. 2. Pleads to the Charge. 3. Upon that Plea is diſcharged by the Judge.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:32414:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">1. A juſtified Perſon muſt be <hi>charg'd with Guilt.</hi> Now Guilt is the Relation which Sin hath to Puniſhment; for Sin is the breach of the Law, and Puniſhment is the Vengeance which the Law threatens for that breach. And as the threatning it ſelf is in the nature of it, a Guard to the Law, to prevent the breach of it, bidding, as it were, the Tranſgreſſor come at his Peril, break the Law if he dare, be wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e before hand, leſt he rue it too late; ſo the Puniſhment in the very nature of it, is a vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Equity of the injur'd Law, the Reparation and Amends it makes it ſelf for the wrong done it, by damnifying the Perſon injuring her, proportionally to the Injury: Now, that a juſtified Perſon muſt be charg'd with Guilt, <hi>i. e.</hi> with the breach of Law; and by conſequence with deſert of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appears, becauſe otherwiſe, if a Man be pronounced Righteous, whom no body ever accuſed, or queſtioned, he is only praiſed, not juſtified.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Perſon to be juſtified, muſt <hi>plead for himſelf;</hi> either in Perſon, or by his Advocate who ſuſtains his Perſon; for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to Plead, is to deſpair quite of being juſtified; and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon ones ſelf over unto Puniſhment, <hi>Silence gives con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> it argues, the accuſed Perſon hath nothing to ſay for himſelf, why he ſhould not be Condemned. Our Law, you know, ſheweth no Mercy to one that will not Plead, he is to be Preſt to Death.</p>
            <p>An Indicted perſon muſt plead therefore ſomething in his own behalf, why he ſhould be Juſtified, if he would be. Now, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Man is Guilty of the Charge, or not Guilty. I muſt ſpeak to both Caſes, and ſhew what Pleas are requiſite in each, and which of them is the Plea upon which a Sinner is juſtified at the Bar of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſe</hi> 1. If the Indicted perſon be <hi>not Guilty</hi> of the Charge, Juſtice it ſelf muſt juſtifie him upon that Plea. <hi>Si accuſaſſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiat, quis erit innocens?</hi> An innocent Perſon may be accuſed, he can never be convinced; for that that is not, can never be demonſtrated; the Judge or Jury were themſelves Guilty, if they found Innocence Guilty. Now to be Juſtified thus, is to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32414:3"/>be purely and meerly Juſtified, not at all to be Pardoned; for ſuch a one ſtands upon his Terms, bears himſelf upon his own Righteouſneſs, begs no Mercy. 'Tis no favour to juſtifie him, 'tis his due; he is not beholding to the Judge a jot, the exact rigor of the Law acquits him.</p>
            <p>To bring this to the preſent Buſineſs, I ſhall demonſtrate, that we can never be juſtified at the Bar of God, by pleading <hi>not Guilty;</hi> For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> The Plea is falſe. Altho' in a very reſtrained Senſe, there is none ſo wicked, but he may plead <hi>not Guilty,</hi> and be juſtified as to this or that particular Fact charged upon him. <hi>Nimrod</hi> was not Guilty of <hi>Abel</hi>'s Murther. Nay, a Saint may be guilty of ſome Sins which the Devil may plead <hi>not Guilty</hi> to, as grieving the comforting, the ſealing Spirit, abuſing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer's Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet nothing ſhort of Univerſal Innocence, nothing but a perfect Righteouſneſs, a total exemption from all manner of Guilt will entitle us before God's Tribunal to this Plea; <hi>For whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, is guilty of all,</hi> Jam. 2.10.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Puniſhment due to the breach of the whole Law, <hi>viz,</hi> the Curſe of God is due to every breach of every part. <hi>Curſed is he that continueth not in all things which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the book of the Law to do them,</hi> Gal. 3.10. Deut. 27.26. <hi>The wages of ſin</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of every ſingle ſin) <hi>is death,</hi> Rom. 6.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe, He that <hi>offends in one point,</hi> affronteth the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of all, as is excellently obſerved in the next Verſe; <hi>For he that ſaid, Do not commit adultery, ſaid alſo, Do not ſteal,</hi> Jam. 2.11. Every Sin hath Atheiſm in it, it denies the God that is above; to trample upon the Majeſty of God ſhining in one Commandment, is at once to trample upon that Majeſty which enacted all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe therby he becomes infected with a contagious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to be guilty of all; the ſame Principle which embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him now, will another time (if but excited with equal Strengths of Temptation) to commit any other Sin, or to repeat the ſame Sins again and again (though excited with ſtill weaker
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32414:4"/>and weaker Temptations) for as frequent Acts ſtrengthen the habit of Sin, ſo the habit facilitates the Acts.</p>
            <p>From hence it appears, That the holy Angels, that <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency, that the Man Chriſt Jeſus, might indeed plead <hi>not Guilty</hi> before God, and be juſtified upon that Plea; but now impoſſible forms, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20, 23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Plea being falſe, there is no h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon this Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue to be juſtified, unleſs there were ſome defect in the Judge, or in the Evidence. In the Judge either of Prudence, in not Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; or of Integrity or Powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in not executing the Law might: But in our Caſe theſe are a like, that is, infinitely impoſſible; for we have to do with the All wiſe Legiſlator him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who is alſo the Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God Almighty, and <hi>ſhall not this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udge of all the earth do right? Gen.</hi> 18.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Nor can there be any defect in the Evidence, for the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ks ſhall <hi>be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened at the laſt day, and the dead ſhall be judged out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f theſe things which are written in the books, according to their works,</hi> Rev. 20.12. Nay, even now there are two Day books a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lling, down goes (every Hour, every Moment) all we do and think, and ſpeak, in the Book of God's Remembrance fairly written; not an <hi>Iota,</hi> not a tittle either miſt or blurred; of this God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us a counterpart to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eep in our own Boſoms, the Regiſter of Conſcience (though a very imperfect Copy, full of Blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, Omiſſions, yet) enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onvince us inſtead of a thouſand Witneſſes; for every Sinner will be his own Accuſer and Condemner, riſing up as an Advocate in the behalf of the great Judge, againſt himſelf at the day of Judgment.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Prima eſt haec ultio, quod ſe</l>
               <l>Judic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o nocen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abſolvitur—</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſe</hi> 2. And this was the firſt Plea, <hi>not Guilty;</hi> but the Caſe is not ours, and therefore this Plea will never juſtifie us. I come therefore to the other (which in our Caſe) <hi>is Guilty;</hi> and here are two ways of pleading. Firſt, <hi>Meer Mercy, for Mercies</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke; but indeed, this is not to Plead at all, but to Beg. And as in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32414:4"/>the laſt Caſe, when an innocent Perſon upon his pleading not Guilty is diſcharged, that is pure Juſtification, but no Pardon: ſo here quite contrary; when a guilty Perſon is diſcharged out of Mercy, this is pure Pardon, but no Juſtification; for there ſhines not one Beam of Juſtice in ſuch a Diſcharge, meer Mercy is all in all. Whence it follows, that the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the neceſſity of acknowledging Chriſt's Satisfaction to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice, affirm, That <hi>Juſtification</hi> is nothing but meer Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, do abuſe <hi>the Word,</hi> and contradict themſelves; for, who ſeeth not, that to be pardoned <hi>gratis,</hi> out of pure Mercy (without the leaſt Reparation made, either for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury and Indignity done to the Law, or Satisfaction to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Juſtice, and Authority of the Law-giver, by the Sin af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted) is not <hi>to be juſtified at all,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but only <hi>to be gratified,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> diſoharged upon the ſole account of Mercy, without any conſideration had of Juſtice. This is the firſt way of plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when <hi>Guilty, meer Mercy for Mercies</hi> ſake; but to be <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> upon this Plea, is an evident Contradiction. Therefore <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> The only Plea for a guilty Perſon to be juſtified upon, is to plead Mercy for the ſake of ſome Satifaction made to the Juſtice and Honour of the Law. And by how much the fuller this Satisfaction is, by ſo much the fullen is the Juſtification of ſuch a perſon as is upon this Plea diſcharged.</p>
            <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as full Satisfaction may be made two ways.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By ſuffering the whole Penalty due.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>When a valuable Conſideration is accepted by the offended Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Judge, wherein the Honour of the Law is as much ſaved, as if it had never been broken; or as if being broken, the full Penalty had been inflicted on the Breaker.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And here I have theſe two things to prove. 1. That Man could never make ſuch Satisfaction to the Juſtice of God, nor any Creature for him. 2. That the Lord Chriſt hath made ſuch full Satisfaction, that it ſtands now with the Honour of the Holy God, to juſtifie Sinners upon the terms of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Aſſertion. First,</hi> That neither Man, nor any Creature, could ſatisfie offended Juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:32414:5"/>
            <p n="1">1. Not by ſuffering the Penalty; for that being Infinite, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an infinite Continuance under it (there being no other way for a Finite Creature to ſuffer Infinitely) and ſo the whole Penalty will ever be ſuffering, but can never be ſuffered; for in Eternity, ſtop where you will, and there is yet as much to come, as is already paſt; nay, infinitely more, for that which is paſt, is but a Finite time of ſuffering, though Millions of Ages are paſt, but an Eternity of ſuffering is yet to come; and after as many more Millions of Ages, ſtill, ſtill an infinite Eternity is future, that never can be ſo exhauſted, but an Eternity will ſtill be left.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Not by any act of Service, which amounts to a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Conſideration worthy to be accepted of the Judge as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory to his affronted Juſtice, for two Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe God is more diſhonoured by one Sin, than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by an Eternity of Obedience; for God is not at all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to <hi>Cherubims</hi> and <hi>Seraphims</hi> for obeying him; all the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation naturally oweth its utmoſt poſſibility of Service, as an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Debt to its great Creator. Now the leaſt act of Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or Sin, being Injury and Treaſon, thereby a new Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is contracted, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſuffer condign Puniſhment, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Obligation unto Duty remaining eternally in as full Force as ever; <hi>which, if we could diſcharge, yet were we but improſitable ſervants,</hi> Luke 17.10. <hi>Can a man be profitable to God?</hi> Job 22.2. <hi>If thou be righteous, what giveſt thou to him? or what recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth be of thine hand?</hi> Job 35.7. An Eternity of Service in the higheſt perfection, is every Creature's Debt as a Creature; and beſide this, an Eternity of ſuffering too, is every delinquent Creature's Debt, as delinquent. But one Debt cannot pay ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſince therefore, all that the whole Creation can do for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, would but juſt ſatisfie the firſt natural Obligation unto <hi>pure Juſtice, viz.</hi> the Debt of Obedience; it is quite impoſſible that ever any Creature ſhould ſupererogate, or ſpare any thing from hence, towards ſatisfying the Secondary ſuper-added Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto <hi>offended Juſtice, viz.</hi> the Debt of Puniſhment, either in its own behalf, or anothers.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32414:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The other Reaſon, why neither Man, nor any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for him, can ever ſatisfie the offended Creator by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Services, becauſe they all have it from him, when they do Obey him; of his own do they give him; for in him we live, and move, and have our Being: What haſt thou, O Man; nay, O Angel, O Arch-angel, that thou haſt not received? All our, nay, all their Springs are in him; without him we can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The more we do for God, the more he doth for us; and conſequently, ſtill the more we owe him. So that acts of Obedience are ſo far from ſatisfying our Obligations to God, as that they contract new ones, for, even for them are we obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Aſſertion.</hi> Having cleared the firſt, we come to the ſecond Point, That Chriſt hath ſo fully ſatisfied his Father's offended Juſtice, as it ſtands now with the Honour of the Holy God, to juſtifie every Sinner, that can upon Goſpel terms, plead his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in this Satisfaction. Here we muſt enquire into theſe three things:
<list>
                  <item>1. The Matter of this Satisfaction.</item>
                  <item>2. The Form, or that which makes it infinitely Satifactory and Meritorious.</item>
                  <item>3. What are thoſe Goſpel terms?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> For the matter of Chriſt's Satisfaction, I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that the whole State of his Humiliation, from his Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Reſurrection (for, at his Reſurrection began the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond State of Chriſt as Mediator, <hi>viz.</hi> his Exaltation to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to the general Reſurrection, and then he ſhall reſign up the Kingdom to the Father, and God ſhall be thenceforward all in all, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, 28.) that this State (I ſay) of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer's Humiliation, is entirely look'd upon by God as the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Conſideration, wherein his Juſtice with Honour acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, and reſts ſatisfied. It hath two Parts. <hi>Firſt,</hi> His taking the form of a Servant at his Incarnation. <hi>Secondly,</hi> His manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of, and deportment in that State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> His Incarnation, and this preſents God with a double Satisfaction, whereby he may with Honour entertain Thoughts of Love to Mankind.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:32414:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. In that, Humane Nature is in Chriſt unſtained with either Original, or Actual Sin; for, by his Divine Conception by the Holy Ghoſt, he received of his Virgin-mother, a pure, unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowred Virgin Humane Nature; the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> revives the Innocency of the firſt; thoſe Eyes could without Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment behold his Manhood, which are purer than to behold Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and even in their ſight, though no other Fleſh living could, yet this Fleſh muſt be juſtified.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that Humane Nature is in him dignified with Union to the Divine, and is become the Seat and Manſion of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; ſo that how loathſom ſoever Sin hath rendred it in us, yet in him it is highly exalted; even as highly, as the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in him was abaſed; for the Humane Nature aſcends juſt in the ſame proportion, as the Divine deſcended, that is, to the utmoſt poſſibility; for God could ſtoop no lower than to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Man, nor Man riſe higher than to be perſonally one with God.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee Chriſt's entring into his State of Humiliation, hath rendred the Nature of Man very conſiderable again in the fight of God; ſo that he can now with Honour, exerciſe good Will towards it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> His management of this State, conſiſts in his active, and paſſive Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>By his active Righteouſneſs, I mean his Obedience to the whole Law; to the Ceremonial, in being Circumciſed, Baptized, keeping the three yearly Feaſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the Moral, in not committing one Sin, or neglecting one commanded Duty, even to Subjection to his Parents, and paying Tribute to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By his paſſive Righteouſneſs, I mean all that he ſuffered in his Life time, as the meanneſs of his Birth and Education; his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution by <hi>Herod</hi> in his Infancy, after by the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi> his Hunger and Temptation in the Wilderneſs, his Poverty and Straits, he had not where to lay his Head; in a word, <hi>He was all his life long in all things tempted as we are (yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin)</hi> Heb. 4.15. but eſpecially what he ſuffered at his Death.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:32414:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> In his Body, he was ſcourged, ſpit upon, crowned with Thorns, and at length Crucified, which was, 1. A cruel Death, the Latin <hi>Cruciari,</hi> to be tormented, is derived, <hi>à cruce,</hi> from being crucified, 2. A reproachful one, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.13. it was the <hi>Roman</hi> Death for Slaves and Malefactors.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Moſt of all he ſuffered in his Soul, witneſs thoſe Expreſſions, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.37. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.33. add his bemoaning himſelf to his Diſciples in the following words, and his paſſionate Prayer thrice repeated, <hi>Abba Father, if it be poſſible let this cup paſs.</hi> Add further yet, his ſweating drops of Blood, in that bitter Agony which ſo ſpent him in the Garden, that an Angel was ſent to comfort him; but above all, his deſertion upon the Croſs, witneſſeth that he ſuffered unut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terably in his Soul, when he cryed, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> The <hi>Socinians</hi> are here puzzled to give any tollerable Account, how the infinitely good God could find in his Heart to exerciſe his only begotten Son, that never ſinned, with all theſe Horrours in his Soul; for certainly, it ſtood not with his Goodneſs, had not Chriſt, as the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> been a publick Perſon, a Repreſentative, <hi>on whom the Lord hath laid the iniquities of us all,</hi> Iſa. 53.6. But if we conſider (which they deny) that Chriſt was then ſatisfying his Father's Juſtice, we need not wonder at thoſe Horrours and Conſternations of the Manhood; for he knew the vaſtneſs of his Undertaking, the numberleſs Numbers, and aggravations of Sins, the dreadful weight of his Father's Wrath, the ſharpneſs of that Sword, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. which he was going now to feel (not that God was angry with Chriſt upon the Croſs, <hi>quoad affectum;</hi> no, he never more dearly loved him, but <hi>quoad effectum</hi>) and Chriſt's infinite Abhorrence of the Sins he bore, and that infinite Zeal wherewith he was inflam'd to vindicate the Honour of Divine Juſtice. Now, his infinite love to his Church ſtruggling with all theſe, produc'd thoſe Agonies, and overcame them all, when he ſaid, <hi>It is finiſhed,</hi> Joh. 19.30. we meet him next triumphing in his Reſurrection.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32414:7"/>
            <p>But here to reſolve that great Queſtion, whether Chriſt's paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Righteouſneſs alone, or Active and Paſſive jointly, are the matter of Chriſt's Satisfaction, which Believers plead at God's Bar for their Juſtification, and, which being accepted by God as a Plea good in Law, is ſaid to be imputed (<hi>viz.</hi> in a Law-ſenſe) for Righteouſneſs. Let theſe Reaſons be weighed by ſuch as do disjoyn them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Each of them hath its proper Intereſt in, and its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Contribution towards the ſatisfying the injur'd Honour of God's Law. For the Honour of God's Law, is the Equity of both its Parts, its Command, and its Threatning; Chriſt's active Righteouſneſs honours the Equity of the firſt, which Man had diſhonoured by his Diſobedience; but the great God-man hath repaired the Honour of God's Commandments, by yielding a moſt perfect Obedience to every one of them, and therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>the Law to be holy, juſt, and good.</hi> Then Chriſt's paſſive Righteouſneſs in like manner honours the Equity of the Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; for, as by <hi>Obeying,</hi> he acknowledged God's Authority to make a Law, and his unexceptionable Righteouſneſs in every ſingle Branch of the Law made; ſo, by <hi>Suffering,</hi> he proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that Man is bound to keep it; or, if he do not, to bear the Penalty. He himſelf dies to juſtifie, that the Sinner is worthy of Death, and offers himſelf upon the Croſs as a Sacrifice to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice; and hereby he hath proclaimed Sin to be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinful, and God to be ſo jealous a God, as, rather than Sin ſhould go unpuniſh'd, and his Juſtice wants its Glory, the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Eternal Son of God muſt be made an Example, what guilty Man had deſerved. Thus God by two equal Miracles (of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Aſtoniſhment to be adored) hath ſatisfied both his contending Attributes, and rendred each of them Triumphant, in making his Righteous Son an Example of his Sin-avenging Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that guilty Sinners (repenting, and believing) might be made Examples of his Sin-pardoning goodneſs.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, as each hath its reſpective Intereſt in ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the injur'd Law, ſo neither of them can be any where ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the other; and thoſe which God hath ſo indiſſolubly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32414:7"/>joyned, let none part aſunder; for Chriſt's active Righteouſneſs was every where paſſive, becauſe, all of it done in the form of a Servant; for in our Nature he obeyed the Law, but in his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Incarnation he was Paſſive, for therein he ſuffered an Eclipſe of the Glory of his God-head. And his paſſive Righteouſneſs was every where active; becauſe, what he ſuffered was not by conſtraint, or againſt his Will; no, it was his own voluntary Act and Deed all along; let me inſtance in the greateſt of his Sufferings, his very dying was the Product both of the freeneſs of his Love, and the Majeſty of his Power, <hi>John</hi> 10.17, 18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>In the third place, Both Chriſt's active and paſſive Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, what he did, and what he ſuffered, partake in common of the <hi>form of ſatisfaction;</hi> therefore, they are both integral parts, or joynt Ingredients thereof; for <hi>forma dat eſſe:</hi> but this brings me to the ſecond Enquiry.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Query,</hi> What is the form of Chriſt's Satisfaction, or that which renders it Satisfactory? I anſwer, the infinite Merit of what he did and ſuffered; which infinite Merit ſtands, 1. In the dignity of his Perſon; the fullneſs of the God-head dwelt in him bodily, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. <hi>John</hi> 1.14. Now for the work of a Servant to be done by the Lord of all, renders his Active; and for him to ſuffer as a Malefactor between Malefactors, who was God bleſſed for evermore, renders alſo his paſſive Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs infinitely Meritorious; no wonder the Blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all Sin, for it is the Blood of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. And this is the Reaſon why the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of one, redounds unto all for <hi>the juſtification of life,</hi> Rom. 5.18, 19. becauſe his active and paſſive Righteouſneſs is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely of more value, than all, that the Creatures in Heaven and Earth could have done, or ſuffered to Eternity; the very Man Chriſt Jeſus is above all the Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. for he is the Man that is God's fellow, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. And this infinite Worthineſs of the Redeemer's Perſon, you have excellently deſcribed, as irradiating, and infinitely exalting all he did and ſuffered, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24, 25, 28.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:32414:8"/>
            <p n="2">2. The active and paſſive Righteouſneſs of Chriſt are of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Merit, becauſe not at all due, but both meer ſupererroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of an infinitely glorious Perſon.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> For his active Righteouſneſs, it ſtood in his Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Ceremonial and Moral Laws.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Obedience to the Ceremonial Law was a meer ſuperer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, for the Subſtance to comply with the Shadows, the Antitype to do homage to its own Types; beſides, he ſubmitted to thoſe very Ordinances, whoſe End and Inſtitution ſuppoſeth Guilt, and whoſe Nature argues them deſigned only for the uſe of Sinners; what foreskin of Impurity had he to be cut off in Circumciſion? what Filth to be waſh'd away in Baptiſm? Did the holy Child Jeſus defile his Mother's Womb. as common Mortals do, that are conceived in Sin, and brought forth in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity? And yet he was Circumciſed and Baptized, and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offered for her Purification, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.21, 22. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.21. No imaginable Obligation lay on him to theſe Submiſſions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him meer Ciphers wholly inſignificant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Obedience to the Moral Law: Although it muſt be granted, that as Man, it was his Duty, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. yet was it not his Duty to become Man. True, a Creature's homage was due from him, when a Creature; a Servant's Work, when in the form of a Servant: but the whole was free and Arbitrary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his entring into that State was ſo: for, what but his own infinite Love could ever move the Eternal Word, to pitch his Tent in our Nature? What Obligation lay on the Heir of all things, to take the form of a Servant? Who bound the Eternal Son of God, to become in the fullneſs of time the Son of Man?</p>
            <p>And as his active Righteouſneſs, ſo <hi>Secondly,</hi> His Paſſive too was a meer Supererrogation; for his Almighty Father's Holy, All-ſeeing Eye, could never eſpy the leaſt Iniquity in him to puniſh: What had the Divine Juſtice to do with him? for he was a ſinleſs Perſon, he ſuffered not for himſelf, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. No, for us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. And therefore, ſince no Obligation lay on him to do what he did, or to ſuffer what he ſuffered, he may impute the Merit both of the one, and the other, to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32414:8"/>and upon what terms ſoever he and his Father pleaſe.</p>
            <p>But before I come to conſider the terms upon which Chriſt's Satisfaction is applied, I muſt anſwer ſome Queſtions, and clear the Scruples in the way.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Object.</hi> 1. What is become of the Law of that firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe? Gen.</hi> 2.17. repeated again to the <hi>Jews, Deut.</hi> 27.26. The ſumme of which you have fully expreſſed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.4. <hi>The ſoul that ſinneth, it ſhall dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, It is not fully executed, nor abrogated, but relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or diſpenſed with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> It is not fully executed; for there is no Condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is not abrogated; for it is in part executed upon Believers; they are liable to the <hi>firſt,</hi> or <hi>natural</hi> Death, <hi>which is the wages of ſin,</hi> although <hi>the ſecond death hath no power over them;</hi> beſides all manner of Chaſtiſements and Afflictions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.30, 31, 32. And alſo that Law is totally executed upon finally Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Unbelievers, over whom not the firſt only, but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death alſo hath Power, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>For he that believeth not, is condemned already,</hi> John 3.18. That is, the Goſpel finds him, and every one in a ſtate of Condemnation; but thoſe who believe, it proclaims Deliverance to; thoſe, who through Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief reject it (judging themſelves unworthy of everlaſting Life, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46.) it leaves ſuch as it found them; <hi>viz,</hi> under the Condemnation of the old Covenant, ſince they refuſe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Mercy of the New.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I anſwer therefore poſitively, That the firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is releaſed, and diſpenſed with, by ſuper-inducing a New Covenant of Grace over it, That whoſoever cloſeth with, and comes into the terms of the New, ſhould be exempted from the Rigor and Extremity, <hi>i. e.</hi> from the Eternal Condemnation of the old, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. It is not ſaid, He that believes ſhall not be Sick, ſhall not be Afflicted, ſhall not Die; <hi>No, but he ſhall not periſh.</hi> Thus you ſee the Covenant of Works, as to its Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon ſuch as are in the Covenant of Grace, is in the chief part reſtrained; but yet in ſome part inflicted: They never ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32414:9"/>under the <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>Deſtructive;</hi> yet they do complain under the <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Corrective</hi> Puniſhment of their Sins, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39.</p>
            <p>Yet more particularly for the clearer underſtanding of this, we muſt conſider that the firſt Covenant lays a double Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on ſinful Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> In reference to what is paſt; and here it requires Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Reparation from us, for our Sin in breaking it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> In reference to the future: after ſuch Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and amends made, it requires perfect Conformity ſtill as at firſt, abſolute Obedience to all God's Commands, being the Eternal Debt of the reaſonable Creature to that God that made it in his own Image: if therefore we could (which hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been proved to be impoſſible) ever have ſatisfied God's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd Law for our paſt breach, the Law would ſtill have come upon us for future, exact Conformity to pay the reſidue of that Eternal Debt: and its Language would be, <hi>Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing befall thee:</hi> as a <hi>Fellon,</hi> though burnt in the Hand, is yet bound to live honeſtly for the future at his Peril. Now the New Covenant of Grace relieves us as to both theſe Caſes, and diſpenſes with the Rigour of the Law.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, It comforts us with the good News, That the Son of God hath ſatisfied his Father's Juſtice; and if we believe but in him, God will accept of us, as if we had ſatisfied in our own Perſons. The caſe the Law leaves us in, is well-expreſſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.51. But the relief the Goſpel brings us in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Language, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. You have both together excellently, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.10, 11.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond Obligation, the New Covenant diſpenſeth with the Rigor of that too: for, woe to a juſtified and pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon, if he muſt loſe all again, upon the leaſt defailance: therefore the Goſpel proclaims pardon of Sin upon Repentance, and acceptance of ſincere Endeavours to obey him. God's Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage now is, Sinners be but in good earneſt, do but love me heartily, and my Ways: let me but ſee a Child-like Ingenuity in you, and I will put down your upright, though imperfect
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32414:9"/>Performances, in the Book of my Remembrance, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. and blot out your Tranſgreſſions, when repented of, out of the Book of my Remembrance. <hi>Mandata Dei tanquam facta repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur, quando quicquid non fit ignoſcitur.</hi> Thus doth the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the Goſpel diſpence with the Rigor of the Law: God deals not with us as an <hi>Aegpptian</hi> Task-maſter, but as a Father with his Children whom he loves: <hi>Chriſt's yoke is eaſie, his burthen light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. If any doubt how it ſtands with God's Veracity, and Immutability, having once declared, that the Soul that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſhall die, to contradict it by declaring that, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth ſhall never die,</hi> but have Eternal Life, <hi>John</hi> 11.26.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, We muſt look upon Threatnings as a part of the Law, declaring the dueneſs of the Puniſhment, what the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hath deſerved to ſuffer; not as Predictions of the Event, any more than <hi>Thou ſhalt,</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhalt not,</hi> in the Command, are Predictions: but only are expreſſive of the dueneſs of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Nor will it hence follow, that we have the leaſt cauſe once to ſuſpect that God may (if he pleaſe) to revoke his Promiſes, as well as his Threatnings; and then, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us? for there is a wide difference in their eſſential Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Properties. In a Promiſe, the Obligation lies upon the Party promiſing; he hath paſt away his own Liberty, and the thing is now no longer his, but the others, who may, if he pleaſe, releaſe, and quit-claim to his Pretenſions; he may diſpenſe with, and ſurrender his own Right; but if he claim his Right to, and Intereſt in the Benefit, by vertue of the Promiſe, it cannot be detained without notorious Wrong and Injury, which, God forbid we ſhould charge him with; for he were not God, if he were not infinitely true and faithful. <hi>How ſhould he elſe judge the world?</hi> But now the Obligation unto Puniſhment lies contraily upon the Sinner threatned; he hath paſt away his own Indemnity, and given God the right of puniſhing him: I ſay the Right, not the Neceſſity; if God will claim this Right, he may; but if he pleaſe, he may diſpenſe with it. It is no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury if he puniſheth; yet no Obligation lies upon him but his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32414:10"/>own Honour, And that, indeed, obligeth him not, never to diſpenſe with his Law; but never to diſpenſe with it upon a light Cauſe, or upon Terms misbecoming his Glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes. And the Diſpenſation we now ſpeak of is an honourable one; for</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are weighty Inducements moving God hereunto. If he had not diſpenſed with the rigour of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> He had loſt the opportunity of the higheſt poſſible way of glorifying his own Goodneſs, which now ſo infinitely endears him to the World, and lays ſuch Obligations on us to admire and adore him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As all <hi>Iſrael</hi> lamented over <hi>Benjamin,</hi> Judg. 21.6. that a Tribe was loſt; ſo the Creation would have miſt a Tribe; which is the reaſon ſome Divines have given why Chriſt <hi>took not on him the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of Abraham;</hi> becauſe, only ſome of the Angelical Tribe loſt their Birth-right; only ſome <hi>kept not their firſt eſtate;</hi> but, <hi>man being in honour continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, but became like the Beaſt that periſheth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> All Religion had been extinguiſh'd, and frozen by Deſpair unavoidably; if there had been no Hope, the Fear of God, his Worſhip and Service had for ever utterly periſh'd from off the Earth. But now <hi>his Name is excellent in all the earth;</hi> even that Name proclaimed to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 34.6. The Lord is known in <hi>Judah,</hi> and his Name is great in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Pſal. 79.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Cauſes inducing are weighty, ſo the Terms on which he diſpenſeth with his Law are as honourable; which was our third <hi>Query</hi> propounded in the opening the Point. For, ſince Chriſt Redeemed us, not by way of Solution (ſtrictly) as a Surety, paying the Debtor's proper Debt to the Creditor; but by way of Satisfaction, as a Mediator and Interceſſor, offering a valuable Conſideration to the offended Judge of the World, in lieu of the Laws executing the Penalty threatned upon the Sinner: It neceſſarily follows, that no Right at all in the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of this Satisfaction can accrue to the Delinquent, but upon ſuch Terms preciſely as the offended Party, and the Mediator that ſatisfieth him, ſhall agree unto; and upon mutual Treaty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32414:10"/>and Com-promiſe, joyntly ratifie; ſo that Juſtification by way of Satisfaction provides, not only the Sinner's Indemnity, but in ſuch a manner, as alſo to conſult the Intereſts and Honour both of the Party ſatisfying, and ſatisfied; and this latter is the rule and meaſure of exhibiting the former, and of making over the Satisfaction for diſcharge of the Offender.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 3. What are the Terms therefore upon which both God and Chriſt have agreed to juſtifie Sinners?</p>
            <p>I anſwer: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Faith, which is a hearty receiving Chriſt as he is tendred by the Goſpel; and here the Soul quits all Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of being juſtified by any Righteouſneſs of its own, and rolls it ſelf upon the Lord its Righteouſneſs; and therefore hath Faith the honour to be the juſtifying Grace, becauſe it ſo highly honoureth Chriſt; it is the Nuptial Knot whereby the Soul joyns it ſelf to its Lord-Redeemer in an everlaſting Marriage-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, it denies it ſelf, and forſakes all its other Lovers, and claſps about its Lord and Husband, as it's all in all. Look what a Wife doth in a Marriage-Covenant to her Husband, that doth a Soul in believing unto Chriſt, it ſaith unto him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thou art my Husband, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.16. And he ſaith unto his Spouſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> you are my People.</p>
            <p>But then this juſtifying Faith hath two Daughters that inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably attend her.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Repentance:</hi> Here ſinful Man retracts and undoes his Faults, cries <hi>peccavi,</hi> weeps, wrings his Hands, ſmites upon his Breaſt, and cries, <hi>What have I done?</hi> Laments after the Lord, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors himſelf in Duſt and Aſhes: He calls himſelf Fool, mad Man, Beaſt, Traytor to his God, and to his Soul: In a word, executes the Law upon himſelf; and ſince God excuſeth him from the Puniſhment, he accuſeth himſelf of the Guilt, and condemns himſelf to the ſhame of his Sin; and hereby the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner honours the Equity of the threatning by his Tears, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that his Blood was due.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Newneſs of Life;</hi> Here the Sinner acknowledgeth perfect Obedience to be ſtill his Duty; this honours the Equity of God's Commandments. And the Redeemer, by making this one of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32414:11"/>the Conditions of the Goſpel-Covenant, hath given his Father his Law back again; he doth not repeal it; no, it's ſtill the rule of Life, and every Commandment ſtill obligeth a Believer. Chriſt hath only releaſed us from the condemning Power of it, not the commanding Power of it. We muſt ſtill preſs after Perfection; but, though we fall ſhort of it, we ſhall not die for it: <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for us;</hi> but hath left us under the Government and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Law. The whole matter is excellently expreſſed, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1. <hi>My little Children, theſe things I write unto you; that you ſin not; and if any man fen, we have an Advocate with the Father Jeſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Having thus diſcourſed to the three general Points firſt propounded, and ſhewed, that the Perſon juſtified is charged with Guilt: And, Secondly, that he pleads to the Charge, (where I have largely opened the nature of that Plea) I come now to the third general Point, to ſhew how <hi>upon his Plea he is diſcharged,</hi> or <hi>juſtified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sinner is then actually juſtified, when he is conſtituted, or made Righteous in Law. Righteouſneſs is a Conformity to the Law; he that fulfills the Law, is Righteous in the Eye of that Law; he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, within the Protection of it; as he that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth the Law, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Guilty in the Eye of the Law, and without the Protection of it. Now the Law of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant runs thus, <hi>He that believeth ſhall not periſh,</hi> ſo, that a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever keeps and fulfills this Law; and therefore <hi>Faith</hi> is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for Righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. becauſe <hi>Faith</hi> is the keeping of the New Covenant, which therefore is called <hi>the Law of Faith,</hi> Rom. 3.27. in oppoſition to the Old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, called there by the Apoſtle, <hi>the Law of Works.</hi> As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Innocency, or perfect Obedience,</hi> would have juſtified <hi>Adam,</hi> had he ſtood by vertue of the Law of Works, or Old Covenant, whoſe Tenour is, <hi>Obey, and Live,</hi> for then he had fulfilled that Law; and as his <hi>Diſobedience</hi> actually condemned him by vertue of the ſame Law, — <hi>Diſobey, and die for it,</hi> Gen. 2.17. So now, believing in Chriſt juſtifieth, by vertue of the Law of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32414:11"/>Faith; for it is the keeping and fulfilling of the Goſpel-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, whoſe Tenour is, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved:</hi> And again, Unbelief actually condemneth by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ſame Law, — <hi>He that believeth not is condemned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, becauſe he hath not believed in the Name of the only begotten Son of God,</hi> John 3.18. That is, becauſe the Unbeliever is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without the Protection of the Goſpel, or Law of Faith, he cometh not up to its Righteouſneſs; he is <hi>condemned already,</hi> as a Sinner, by the Law of Works; and yet once more with a Witneſs, condemned as an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever,</hi> as a Monſter that hath twice been acceſſary to his own Murther: <hi>Firſt,</hi> in wounding himſelf, and <hi>Secondly,</hi> in refuſing to be healed: The Law of Works includes us all under Sin, we <hi>are all dead,</hi> our Caſe was deſperate; but <hi>God who is rich in mercy, through his great love wherewith he hath loved us,</hi> Epheſ. 2.4. (his immenſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) when we were dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, <hi>hath ſent his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life,</hi> John 3.16. And this is that Law accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which he will judge the World; <hi>according to my Goſpel,</hi> faith <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 2.27. Every Believer therefore, though he wants the Righteouſneſs of the Law of Works (<hi>viz.</hi> Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) yet he ſhall not be condemned, becauſe he hath the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Goſpel (<hi>viz.</hi> Faith) which is the New Law in force, according to which, God now dealeth with us, and ſhall judge the World at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>And here it will be richly worth our very heedful Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that although a Believer hath not the Righteouſneſs of the Law of Works, inherent in himſelf: (for if he had, he were not a Sinner, but ſhould be juſtified by that Law) yet by Faith he lays hold upon Chriſt's Satisfaction, which in the very Eye of the Law of Works is an unexceptionably Perfect, and infinitely glorious Righteouſneſs: So that Faith juſtifieth us even at the Bar of the Law of Works, <hi>Ratione objecti,</hi> as it lays hold on Chriſt's Satisfaction, which, is our legal Righteouſneſs; it juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth us at the Bar of the Goſpel, or Law of Faith, <hi>formaliter, &amp; ratione ſui,</hi> as it is Covenanting-keeping, or a fulfilling of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32414:12"/>Goſpel-Law: For, he that keeps a Law is Righteous, where that Law is Judge, the Law-maker by his very making of the Law, makes him Righteous, and the Judge that pronounceth according to the Law (for a Judge is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) will infallib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pronounce him ſo.</p>
            <p>But that with all requiſite Diſtinctneſs we may apprehend this great Affair, let us take a view of ſome of the moſt conſiderable and important Cauſes which concur to the producing this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Effect, the diſcharge and juſtification of a Sinner, and ſtate their ſeveral Intereſts and Concernments in their reſpective In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences upon, and Contributions towards it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> How free grace juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> The free Grace of God is the firſt Wheel that ſets all the reſt in motion. Its Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution is that of a <hi>Proegumenal Cauſe,</hi> or Internal Motive, diſpoſing God to ſend his Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>That ſinners</hi> (believing) <hi>might be juſtified freely by his grace, through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 3.24. For Chriſt died not to render God good (he was ſo Eternally) but that with the Honour of his Juſtice he might exert and diſplay his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which contriv'd and made its ſelf this way to break forth into the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> How Chriſts Satisfaction.</note> Chriſt's Satisfaction is doubly concern'd in our Juſtification.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of God, as a <hi>Procatartick Cauſe</hi> of infinite Merit, and Impetrative Power; for the ſake of which God is reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelf unto the World in Chriſt, not imputing their Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of the Law of Works, Chriſt's Satisfaction juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us formally, as our proper legal Righteouſneſs; I call it <hi>our Righteouſneſs,</hi> becauſe it becomes imputed to us upon our Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; Faith being our Goſpel Title, by pleading which, we lay claim to all the Benefits accruing from the Merit of Chriſt's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, to all Effects, Uſes and Purpoſes, as if it had been perſonally our own; I call it <hi>our legal Righteouſneſs,</hi> becauſe, thereby the Law of God owns it ſelf fully apaid, and acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in it, as in full Reparations and Amends made unto it, for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32414:12"/>the injury and diſhonour received by the Sin of Man. We muſt plead this againſt all the Challenges and Accuſations of the Law: who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of God's Elect? it is Chriſt that died, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rom. 8.33. And thus our legal Righteouſneſs required in the firſt Covenant, that of Works, is wholly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us in our Redeemer, yet imputed upon our Account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Goſpel juſtifieth <hi>quâ Lex lata,</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> How the Goſpel.</note> as it is the Law of Faith; for the very Tenour of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Covenant, is, Believe, and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Faith juſtifieth <hi>vi Legis latae,</hi>
               <note n="4" place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> How Faith.</note> as it is our Evangelical Righteouſneſs, or our keeping the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Law? for that Law ſuſpends <hi>Juſtification</hi> upon <hi>Believing.</hi> Faith pretends to no Merit or Vertue of its own, but profeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avows its dependance upon the Merit of Chriſt's Satisfaction, as our legal Righteouſneſs, on which it layeth hold, nor can it ſhew any other Title to be it ſelf our Evangelical Righteouſneſs, but only God's Sanction, who choſe this Act of believing to the honour of being the Juſtifying Act, becauſe it ſo highly honoureth Chriſt; ſo that as a moſt judicious Pen expreſſeth it, the Act of Believing is as the Silver; but God's Authority in the Goſpel-Sanction, is the King's Coin, or Image Stamp'd upon it, which gives it all its value as to Juſtification. Without this Stamp it could never have been currant; and if God had ſet this Stamp on any other Grace as Love, that then would have been currant, and have juſtified us as Faith doth now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> God juſtifieth in a proper ſenſe two ways:<note n="5" place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> How God.</note> 
               <hi>First,</hi> As a Legiſlator: <hi>Secondly,</hi> As a Judge.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As a Legiſlator, enacting by his Soveraign Authority, that fweet and gracious Law of the New Covenant, by vertue of whoſe Tenour, every Sinner that believes is juſtified from the Guilt of Sin; <hi>from which he could not be juſtified by the Law of Moſes,</hi> Acts 13.38, 39. This Law of Juſtification by Faith, is God's own Act and Deed, the great <hi>Inſtrumentum pacis,</hi> between God and Man: he hath proclaimed his Letters Patents; the King of Heaven and Earth hath in the Goſpel (our <hi>Magna Charta</hi>) given his Warrant under his own Broad Seal, <hi>That he that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſhall not be condemned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32414:13"/>
            <p n="2">2. As a Judge, the God of Heaven may in three reſpects be ſaid to juſtifie a Believer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Forthwith upon his Believing, God owneth him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly within himſelf, as a Perſon juſtified; God eſteems and approves of him as in that ſtate, unto which he hath, by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Title good in Law, an indefeaſible Right; a juſtified E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate emergeth actually, as ſoon as Faith; the Law-Title there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto emergeth as a neceſſary Reſultance by virtue of the Tenour of the Goſpel-Law, which only juſtified Virtually, Potentially, and Conditionally before every Believer in general; but now Actually, Abſolutely, and in particular, it juſtifieth him as a Believer when he is ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> At the moment of Diſſolution God juſtifieth as the Judge of all the Earth, paſſing a private Sentence and Award unto everlaſting Life upon every believing Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> But Eminently at the laſt Day, when the Ancient of Days ſhall take the Throne, and in open Court, before the whole Creation, by publick Sentence for ever acquit and diſcharge Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers at that great and laſt Aſſizes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi>
               <note n="6" place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> How Works.</note> Shall I need to add, that Works are ſaid to juſtifie us? <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.4. becauſe they juſtifie our Faith, or demonſtrate before God and Man, and to our own Conſciences, that our Faith is not a dead and barren, but a true and living one by its fruitfulneſs in well-doing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi>
               <note n="7" place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> How the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> But I muſt not forget, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That the Spirit of God is ſaid to juſtifie us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. and that two ways. <hi>Firſt, Directly,</hi> by working Faith in the Heart, which is one of the Fruits of the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. Now, <hi>Cauſa cauſae eſt etiam cauſa cauſati;</hi> the Spirit juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as it is the Author of the juſtifying Grace. <hi>Secondly, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexibly:</hi> The Divine Spirit clears up Juſtification to a Believer's Conſcience, by diſcovering the truth of Faith, by working Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, and by ſealing a Believer to the day of Redemption. <hi>The Spirit it ſelf beareth witneſs with our ſpirits, that we are the Children of God; and if Children, then heirs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16, 17.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32414:13"/>
            <p>Thus I have at length done with my firſt Task, the <hi>opening of the Point,</hi> which finds its ſelf ſummed up in this Definition; <hi>Juſtification is a judicial act of God, as Law-giver and Judge of the world, graciouſly diſcharging a Believer for the ſake of Chriſt's ſatisfaction, from the condemnation of the Law of Works, by the tenour of the Goſpel-Law, or New Covenant, which requireth of, accepteth from, imputeth unto ſinners faith in Chriſt Jeſus as their righteouſneſs;</hi> ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe. Refut.</hi> To improve it now (which was my other Task) by way of Refutation, I infer againſt the <hi>Antinomians, Firſt,</hi> That Juſtification is not from Eternity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe a perſon muſt be charged with Guilt before he is juſtified or diſcharged; but nothing can be before Eternity; if diſcharg'd from Eternity, when was he charged? what, from Eternity too? then he will be at once eternally charged with, and diſcharged from Guilt, which, if any excuſe from a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, they are much wiſer than I am.</p>
            <p n="2">2. My Text convinceth them, actual Faith is not from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, therefore not Juſtification before God; for if Faith juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us not before God, but only at the Bar of Conſcience; then there will be no Juſtification at God's Bar at all once mention'd in Scripture; for Works do it at Man's Bar. What is it I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that juſtifieth from Eternity? Not God's Decree to juſtifie; for then his Decree to glorifie, would make Glorification from Eternity too; — but <hi>Decreta Dei nihil ponúnt actu in ſubjecto.</hi> God's Decrees are immanent Acts, and paſs nothing actually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Creature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A juſtified perſon was actually under Condemnation whil'ſt he was an Unbeliever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.18. <hi>He that believeth not, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already;</hi> but he could not be at all Condemned, if ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified from Eternity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly affirms, that the believing <hi>Corinthians</hi> were not once, but now were juſtified, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. Such were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:32414:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I infer againſt them, that are dangerouſly miſtaken, in thinking that a Believer is Righteous in the ſight of God, with the ſelf-ſame active and paſſive Righteouſneſs wherewith Chriſt was Righteous, as though Believers ſuffered in Chriſt, and obeyed in Chriſt, and were as Righteous in God's Eſteem as Chriſt himſelf, having his perſonal Righteouſneſs made perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theirs by Imputation. This is their fundamental miſtake, and from hence <hi>(tanquam ex equo Trojano)</hi> iſſue out a throng of ſuch falſe and corrupt Deductions and Conſequences as theſe.</p>
            <p>That God ſees no Sin in his Children; that Affliction and Death are not proper Puniſhments of Sin to Believers: that all future Sins are already actually forgiven, as well as paſt and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; that a Believer muſt not pray for the Pardon of Sin, but only for the manifeſtation of it; that God loved <hi>Noah</hi> when drunk; <hi>Lot,</hi> when ſo, and beſide inceſtuous; <hi>David,</hi> when acting Adultery and Murther; <hi>Peter,</hi> when he was curſing and ſwearing, and denying Chriſt, with as high a love of Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Delight, as when converſant in the moſt ſpiritual Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of Grace; that all which God requires as a Sinner's Duty in the Goſpel, is to believe that Chriſt died abſolutely for him in particular; that this is all true Goſpel-Faith; and the doubting or queſtioning this, the unbelief which the Goſpel ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth; that, to argue our Juſtification from our Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and gather aſſurance of God's Love from our Love and Fear of him, is a legal Principle; that Obedience to God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments is not properly a Believer's Debt, but, that all the Obligation which lies upon him to Holineſs, is only the volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expreſſion of his love and gratitude to God, not as what is due, but what is comely: And laſtly, (for I ſhould be tired to name all) that Chriſt hath kept the Goſpel-Covenant for us, as well as ſatisfied the Law; ſo that not only our Legal Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is without us in Chriſt our Surety, but our Evangelical Righteouſneſs it ſelf alſo.</p>
            <p>Now to pluck up all theſe deſperate Conſequences by the Root, there needs no more than a right underſtanding of the true and proper Notion, and manner of Chriſt's redeeming us;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32414:14"/>it is not by way of <hi>Solution,</hi> but of <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> Clearly thus, our Caſe to God is not properly that of <hi>Debtors,</hi> but that of <hi>criminal Subjects.</hi> God's Aſpect to us-ward, not properly that of a <hi>Creditor,</hi> but that of a <hi>Rector</hi> and <hi>Judge:</hi> The perſon Chriſt ſuſtained, and the part he acted, not in a ſtrict ſenſe that of a Surety, paying the very Debt in kind, and ſo diſcharging a Bond; but that of a Mediator expiating our Guilt, and making Reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Divine Juſtice another way than by the execution of the Law. And indeed, the very nature of a Law is ſuch, as it is quite impoſſible that the Obligation either of its Threatning or Command, ſhould in a proper ſenſe be fulfilled, by any other than the very perſon threatned and commanded; <hi>alias</hi> here makes <hi>aliud.</hi> If another ſuffer the Penalty, the threatning is not fulfilled: Nor if another performs the Duty, the Command: for the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation as to Puniſhment lies on the perſon threatned <hi>(noxa caput ſequitur)</hi> and that to Duty on the perſon Commanded, it cannot be fulfilled in kind by another, but it ceaſes to be the ſame thing, and becomes another thing from that in the Obligation; yet it may be ſuch <hi>another thing</hi> (and Chriſt's Righteouſneſs (both active and paſſive) really is ſuch) as the Rector or Judge may accept of with Honour, and be ſatisfied with, as if the very ſame thing had been ſuffered and done juſt in the ſame manner, as the Law threatned and commanded it.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt hath paid not the <hi>Idem,</hi> but <hi>Tantundem,</hi> i. e. not fulfilled the Law (as for us) in kind, but ſatisfied it for us, is moſt evident. For,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Law obliged the Sinner's perſon to ſuffer; Chriſt was no Sinner.</item>
                  <item>2. All Men to ſuffer, foraſmuch as all had Sinned; Chriſt was but one Man.</item>
                  <item>3. The Puniſhment due by Law was Eternal; Chriſt ſuffered but for a ſeaſon, and is entred into his Glory; thus Chriſt paid not the ſame thing that was in the Obligation, but ſomething equivalent thereunto.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This being obtain'd, that the Lord Chriſt hath Redeemed us, not by way of Solution, or diſcharging a Bond, by payment in kind, but by way of Satifaction, or making Amends to the injur'd Juſtice of the Law: It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows from the Reaſon and Nature of the thing:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God pardons freely; we are not only beholding to Chriſt for ſatisfying, but to God too infinitely, for accepting of any Satisfaction at all; he might have refuſed it; he had done Sinners no wrong if he had executed the Rigour of the Law, without hearkening to terms of Reconciliation. Quite contrary, a Creditor doth not pardon the Debtor, when the Surety hath diſcharged the Bond by full payment in kind; the Debtor is beholding indeed to his Friend the Surety, but not all to the Creditor, who cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to cancel the Bond; nay, it were wrong and injuſtice in him if he did.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That none hath, or can have actual Intereſt in, or Benefit by this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, but upon ſuch terms as God and Chriſt have mutually compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in, and agreed to, <hi>viz.</hi> the conditions of the Goſpel-Covenant above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. See the anſwer to the third Query.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:32414:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Reaſon hereof is partly from God, the injur'd Law-giver of the World; who ſeeing it was at his liberty to accept of Satisfaction or no, hath of neceſſity the right to make his own terms, when, and how far forth, and in what manner and method he will condeſcend to admit the Sinner to the actual benefit of Chriſt's Satisfaction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And partly too from Chriſt; for as he is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man, a friend to both Parties; nay, a perſon conſiſting of both Natures; the offended and offending; he is ingaged neceſſarily by virtue both of Office and Perſon, to eſpouſe with equal tenderneſs of regard the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of both Parties; for he is really concerned in them both; they are his Concernments as well as theirs. True indeed, a Surety that diſchargeth a Bond by full payment in kind, he ſuſtains and bears only the perſon of the Debtor, minds only his <hi>Indemnity,</hi> doth what he doth upon his Account, and for his ſake. But our great <hi>Mediator</hi> muſt conſult not only our <hi>Impunity,</hi> but his Father's, yea, and his own Honour; and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, get you hence all you that either yet never did, or that do not now repent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and conſcientiouſly endeavour to obey; here's not the leaſt jot of Benefit for you in the caſe you are in, from this Redemption: for, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſoever the Merit of Chriſt's Satisfaction is, it conferreth nothing actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon any perſon that hath not actually a Goſpel-claim and Title to plead it before God. The immediate effect actually reſulting from Chriſt's performance, is the procuring the Goſpel-Covenant to be ratified by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as a Law, whereby Sinners upon the terms propounded, become re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable unto God; actually it is of force to all that have, but to none that want the Conditions of it. Now the keeping this Goſpel-Covenant, God expects from us in perſon (tho' by the Aſſiſtance of his Spirit, which he hath promiſed to give to them that humbly and earneſtly ask it of him, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.1.) To affirm that Chriſt hath kept the Goſpel for us too, is to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the moſt ſelf-contradicting Blaſphemy and Abſurdity imaginable; as if he could repent, or believe in himſelf, free, except, or cancel our Obligation to obey the Moral Law, by his own obeying it; as if Chriſt had ſo done all, that nothing remains to be done on our part. Such ſtrange extreams do ſome Men run into, that to avoid Juſtification by Works (by an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) are as yet extravagant on the other hand, thinking the Grace of God cannot be free, except the Sinner become either a ſenſeleſs Statue, meerly paſſive, or (which is yet worſe) have a writ of eaſe to be quite idle, or (which is worſt of all) a Licenſe to Sin by Prerogative. Let the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> chaſtiſe this Inſolence, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.15 <hi>ſhall we ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are not under the Law, but under grace? God forbid.</hi> If Chriſt had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the Law for us in the ſenſe of paying a Debt, or diſcharging a Bond, the Apoſtles anſwer could not ſtand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e them make void the Law through Faith? yea, we eſtabliſh the Law.</hi> When a Believer breaks the Law, he Sins <hi>(for ſin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law)</hi> nay, he cannot break it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32414:15"/>willfully, but he breaks the very Goſpel-Covenant (one Condition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſincere Obedience) and the guilt of that ſin lieth upon him unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, until by hearty Repentance, and freſh Applications by Faith to the Blood of ſprinkling (which are the only Titles good in Law, the only Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-claims to Pardon) he hath ſued out a new Pardon (for actual Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is only of paſt Sins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.) according to the Tenour of the New Covenant, which is a perpetual Law of pardoning, repenting and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Sinners, whomſoever, whenſoever, but as ſuch.</p>
            <p>Neither was Chriſt's ſuffering like the cancelling of a Bond, a total diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of us, from ſuffering the Penalty threatned in the Law; we die ſtill, and Afflictions are Puniſhments ſtill. True indeed upon Chriſt's Satisfaction made, God and he are agreed, that a believing Sinner ſhould not be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the everlaſting deſtructive Penalty threatned <hi>(for whoſoever believes ſhall not periſh)</hi> Joh. 3.16. but they are not, that he ſhall not be, for he is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the temporal corrective Puniſhments of the threatning, as Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and natural Death; yet, even theſe (through infinite Goodneſs ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſpoſing it) prove much more a Benefit, than a Penalty to a Believer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. What cauſe have we then with the loweſt and profoundeſt Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to adore the Majeſty of the living God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To adore his Holineſs. Reverence <hi>thoſe eyes of his, that are purer than that they can endure to behold iniquity,</hi> Hab. 1.13. Let this God be thy dread and awe. Dare not to make a mock of Sin; tremble at the horrid Guilt and ſinfulneſs of the leaſt Sin; look upon it as an Affront and Treaſon againſt an Eternal Majeſty, as worthy the Curſe of the Law, and the Wrath of an Almighty God, as that which could not be expiated at a leſſer rate than the Blood of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To adore his Wiſdom in finding out ſuch a perſon to ſatisfie his Juſtice as our Redeemer; conſider here, that God could not ſuffer, could not die; nay, could not (properly) ſatisfie himſelf; (for it had not been a Satisfaction to his Juſtice at all, but <hi>meer Mercy;</hi> and ſo no Juſtification of a Sinner, but <hi>meer Pardon,</hi> if the perſon ſatisfying had been only God.) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, conſider, that a meer Creature could never ſatisfie, as I before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated a meer Creature had periſh'd in the Attempt, would have been overwhelm'd, and cruſh'd to pieces with that inſupportable Load, the guilt of Sin, and the wrath of God. The perſon therefore that muſt fatisfie, muſt neither be Finite, nor Infinite, neither the Creature, nor the Creator; neither God nor Man; yet muſt be both. Here now, the Underſtandings of Men and Angels muſt have been tryed to all Eternity, and loſt for ever in a bottomleſs Gulf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Horrour and Amazement to find out ſuch a Perſon. <hi>O the depth of the riches of the wiſdom and knowledge of God!</hi> Rom. 11.33. <hi>ſee alſo</hi> Epheſ. 1.7, 8. <hi>fully hereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To adore the Infinite Riches of his Grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. in Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; and here conſider,</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:32414:16"/>
            <p n="1">1. God might have let man alone, ſeized the forfeiture; as the Tree fell, it might have lain for ever; what obliged God to accept of Satisfaction?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Redeemer hath <hi>trodden the Wine preſs alone;</hi> what ever was done in this Satisfaction, he did it; <hi>Of the People there was none with him.</hi> The Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath not the leaſt hand in it, could not pay one, Chriſt paid every one to the utmoſt farthing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It was the Judge himſelf who contrived this way to Juſtifie us, and it was at his coſt, he gave his Son; herein God commended his Love to us, as <hi>Abraham</hi> once did his faith to God, in that he ſpared not his Son, his only begotten Son whom he Loved. So that if we rightly weigh it, it will appear, that by how much the Satisfaction is the fuller, by ſo much the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is the freer; by how much his Juſtice is the more, by ſo much too is his mercy the more glorified, and ſtill, ſtill infinitely the more are we obliged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 3. <hi>Conſol.</hi> Here's unſpeakable comfort for every humble, though doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soul, every contrite Spirit that Hungers and Thirſts after Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider how full Satisfaction Chriſt hath made, he is able to ſave to the utmoſt all that come to God through him; he is the beloved Son in whom the Father is well-pleaſed; all power is committed into his hands; God hath exalted him to be a Prince, and a Saviour to give Repentance, and Remiſſion of ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider he inviteth thee as a Sinner to come in unto this Goſpel-righteouſneſs, in the general tenour of his Proclamation, Whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any man Sin, we have an Advocate with the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>An whoſoever,</hi> excludes none that excludes not himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider Chriſt aſſures thee (that art the Perſon I now ſpeak to) he who is the Truth aſſures thee thou ſhalt be welcome: <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt,</hi> &amp;c. This is your very caſe: Hark, the <hi>Maſter calleth you,</hi> will you not be of good courage, and <hi>Go,</hi> when he ſaith <hi>Come!</hi> he that never yet caſt out any that came unto him, that never will, he ſaith ſo himſelf; Thou maiſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him, he never broke his Word yet, he will not begin with thee, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider thoſe ſtanding Monuments of Gods free Juſtifying grace that are on record in the Scripture. What hath been done, may be done again: Nay, will be done again (in the caſe we ſpeak of) by the God that changeth not; God hath pardoned as great Sinners; ſee <hi>Ephraims</hi> caſe <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18. ſee the <hi>Corinthians</hi> example, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10, 11. ſee <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Whoever goes and doth likewiſe, ſhall receive likewiſe; for Chriſt is yeſterday and to day, and the ſame for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Conſider it is the very deſign of God in giving his Son, and of Chriſt in giving himſelf to die for us, to Juſtifie ſuch as thou art, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 16.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.19, 20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.12. 1. <hi>John</hi> 5.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 4. <hi>Exhort.</hi> Firſt, To the Unconverted.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32414:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 4. <hi>Exhort.</hi> Let me then beſeech Sinners not to love Death; Why ſhould iniquity be your ruin? <hi>There is Balm in Gilead, there is a Phyſician there?</hi> Why are ye unwilling to be healed? Turn ye, Turn ye, why will ye die? Would it be a hard matter to perſwade a Condemned Perſon to be willing not to be Executed, were he not diſtracted? If having a pardon offered upon the eaſie Terms of confeſſing his fault, and ſerious promiſing Amendment, he ſhould bid the Prince keep his Pardon to himſelf; for his part, he was in love with his Chains, he would not be Releaſed, he would die. Thou art the man whoever thou art that neglecteſt Goſpel-grace; what Fury and Raging madneſs is it that thou art Guilty of? Thy Soul with all its Eternal intereſts lies at Stake, and as if it were neither here nor there, what became of thee for ever, thou <hi>deſpiſeſt the riches of Gods forbearance, after thy hardneſs and impenitent heart, treaſuring up wrath againſt the day of wrath;</hi> Rom. 2.4, 5. Is it well done of thee Sinner? is this thy kindneſs to thy own Soul? is this thy thanks to thy Redeemer? How inexcuſable art thou? thy ſelf being Judge, thou can'ſt not anſwer it to thy Conſcience, to thy God, with the leaſt Colour or Shadow of a reaſon. God ſends his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Proclaiming, — <hi>Repent ye, and be converted, that your ſins may be blottted out:</hi> Acts 3.19. His Miniſters Proclaiming, — We then <hi>are Embaſſadours of Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us; we pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye reconciled unto God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. Why doſt thou hate thy Soul, and ſay I will not? why wilt thou not? Is it becauſe it doth not concern thee? or becauſe Eternal Life and Death are trifles, ſmall, little things, not worth thy conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering? or doth any body hinder thee? No, no; our Saviour gives the true account, <hi>Ye will not come unto me that ye might have life.</hi> Let me intreat this ſmall requeſt of thee for Gods ſake, for thine own, take the next opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and ſpend half an hour alone; let thy Spirit accompliſh a diligent ſearch, purſue this inquiry to ſome Iſſue; am I Juſtified or no? if not, what will become of me, if it ſhould happen (ſometimes ſuch things fall out) that I ſhould die now preſently? I cannot promiſe my ſelf that I ſhall ſee to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row morning. Thus go on and bring it to ſomething before thou leaveſt; give not over till thou art not only clearly convinced of, but heartily affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thy Guilt; not only to ſee, but ſeel thy ſelf to be the Man who art undone without an Intereſt in this Juſtification. Be in good earneſt; thou canſt not mock thy God; and is there any Wiſdom in mocking and cheating thy own Soul? What thou do'ſt, do it heartily as unto the Lord, as for thy life, as one that would not rue thy ſelf-deceiving folly, when it cannot be recalled; and if thou art hearty and ſerious in theſe Reflections,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thou wilt deeply humble thy ſelf before the Majeſty of the Judge of all the Earth, with that ſelf-abhorrence and Confuſion, that becomes one who feels himſelf (even himſelf being Judge) moſt righteouſly condemned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou wilt Sollicite and Aſſail the Throne of Grace with all redoubled favours, and Holy Paſſionate Importunities of Prayer and Supplication, giving
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32414:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>God no reſt till he hath given thee his Spirit, according to his own promiſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 27. To help thee to perform the conditions of the Goſpel Covenant, plead his own promiſe with him. Wreſtle with him for a broken and clean Heart; for Faith, for Repentance unto Life; for theſe are not of thy ſelf, they are the Gift of God, let him not go till he hath Bleſſed thee with theſe Bleſſings in Chriſt Jeſus. This will confound every Sinner at the day of Judgement, that when he might have had grace; yea, the Spirit of Grace for asking; he either asked not, or if he did, it was ſo cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if he were contented enough to go without. Now if thou art in good earneſt, God is I aſſure thee in full as good earneſt as thou; he is ready to meet thee; try but once whether it be in vain to ſeek him; all that ever tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, found it good to draw near to God, and found him eaſie to be entreated; he uſeth not to ſend the Hungry empty away. He that commands us to <hi>work out our Salvation with fear and trembling, he it is that worketh in us both to will and to do of his own good pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2.12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To them that are the Children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, Let me beſeech them,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To walk Worthy of God who hath called them to his Kingdom and Glory, to adorn their Holy Profeſſion; take the Exhortation in <hi>Pauls</hi> words, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. <hi>As ye have received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walk ye in him,</hi> Receive not this Grace of God in vain; the intereſt of your comfort obligeth you hereunto; hereby you will know that you know him, that you <hi>are in Chriſt Jeſus that there is no condemnation</hi> to you, if you <hi>walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.1. and herein will your <hi>Father be glorified, if ye bring forth much fruit;</hi> Joh. 15.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To live up to the Comforts of their State, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1. you are already <hi>the Sons of God,</hi> it doth not yet appear what you ſhall be, <hi>who ſhall lay any thing to your charge, it is God that Juſtifies: who is he that condemns? it is Chriſt that died,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 8.33. <hi>Go eat thy Bread with joy, and put on thy white raiment, God now hath accepted thy works,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.7, 8. I conclude this particular (and the whole Diſcourſe) with the happy effects and proofs of Jufication which every believer hath as good a Right and Title to, as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel it ſelf, the Word of the God of Truth can give him, as I find by thoſe ſweet Effects and Conſequences ſet down in my Text, and the words next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. 1. <hi>Therefore being Juſtified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> 2. <hi>By whom alſo we have acceſſe by faith, into this grace wherein we ſtand, and rejoyce in hope of the Glory of God.</hi> 3. <hi>And not only ſo, but we glory in tribulations alſo, knowing that tribulation worketh patience:</hi> 4. <hi>And patience experience: and experience hope:</hi> 5. <hi>And hope maketh not aſhamed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts, by the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us.</hi> wherefore <hi>the righteous ſhall be glad in the Lord, and all the upright in heart ſhall glory;</hi> Pſal. 64.10.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
